Nicholas Longworth Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Nicholas Longworth Papers 1782-1931 (bulk 1915-1930)
MSS55129
Longworth, Nicholas, 1869-1931
1,800 items
4 containers plus 2 oversize
2.4 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Lawyer, congressman, and speaker of the United States House of Representatives. Correspondence, speeches, newspaper clippings, scrapbooks, and memorabilia consisting chiefly of speeches made during Longworth’s servce in the House of Representatives. Includes a series of letters to Theodore Roosevelt concerning the nomination of an African American to be surveyor of customs for the Port of Cincinnati; a group of letters by Longworth's grandfather, Nicholas Longworth (1782-1863); and an album of letters of speakers of the United States House of Representatives.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Longworth, N. (Nicholas), 1782-1863--Correspondence.; Longworth, Nicholas, 1869-1931.; Roosevelt, Theodore, 1858-1919--Correspondence.
Organizations
Harvard University--Students.; United States. Congress. House.; United States. Congress. House. Office of the Speaker of the House--Correspondence.
Subjects
African Americans--Ohio--Cincinnati.; Universities and colleges--Massachusetts.
Places
United States--Politics and government--1901-1953.
Occupations
Lawyers.; Representatives, U.S. Congress--Ohio.
Provenance
The papers of Nicholas Longworth, lawyer, congressman, and speaker of the United States House of Representatives, were given to the Library of Congress by Katherine F. Deitz in 1964 and by his granddaughter, Joanna Sturm, in 1975.
Transfers
Items have been transferred from the Manuscript Division to other custodial divisions of the Library. Photographs have been transferred to the Prints and Photographs Division. Sheet music has been transferred to the Music Division. All transfers are identified in these divisions as part of the Nicholas Longworth Papers.
Related Material
Other material relating to Nicholas Longworth is in the Manuscript Division’s collection of the papers of his wife, Alice Roosevelt Longworth.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of Nicholas Longworth are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1869, Nov. 5 Born, Cincinnati, Ohio
1891 Graduated, Harvard College, Cambridge, Mass.
1894 Graduated, Cincinnati Law School, Cincinnati, Ohio
1891 Elected to the Cincinnati Board of Education, Cincinnati, Ohio
1899 1901 Member, Ohio state house of representatives
1901 1903 Member, Ohio state senate
1903 1913 Represented 1st District of Ohio in the United States Congress
1906 Married Alice Lee Roosevelt
1915 1931 Represented 1st District of Ohio in the United States Congress
1923 1925 Republican Party floor leader, United States House of Representatives
1925 1932 Speaker, United States House of Representatives
1931, Apr. 9 Died, Aiken, S.C.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Nicholas Longworth (1869-1931) span the period 1782-1931. Most of Longworth’s papers were destroyed during the closing of his home, Rookwood, in Cincinnati following his death. What remains consists of miscellaneous correspondence, newspaper clippings relating to political campaigns, scrapbooks from his student years at Harvard College, souvenir memorial books, and speeches.
A series of letters from various individuals written in 1907 to President Theodore Roosevelt concerns nomination of an African American to be surveyor of customs of the port of Cincinnati. Letters written by Longworth’s grandfather, Nicholas Longworth (1782-1863), are dated 1823, 1824, and 1860.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is arranged in four series:
Correspondence, 1823-1928
Speeches and Writings, 1889-1930
Miscellany, 1782-1931
Oversize, 1782-1920
Container List
- Correspondence, 1823-1928 (Box 1)
  Letters sent and received and letters to Theodore Roosevelt from others.
  Arranged by category and chronologically therein.
  - Longworth, Nicholas (1782-1863), 1823-1824, 1860 (Box 1)
  - Longworth, Nicholas (1869-1931), 1902-1906, 1923-1924, 1928, undated
  - Roosevelt, Theodore (1858-1919), letters concerning appointment of surveyor of customs, Port of Cincinnati, 1907
- Speeches and Writings, 1889-1930 (Box 1-2)
  Holograph and typed speeches and a copy of Silas Jackson’s Wrongs by Longworth (1869-1931).
  Arranged chronologically.
  - Book, Silas Jackson’s Wrongs (1889) (Box 1)
  - Speeches
    - Chronological file
      - 1906-1923, (7 folders)
      - 1924-1930, undated, (8 folders) (Box 2)
    - Extracts from the Congressional Record; Remarks by Nicholas Longworth, 1904-1911
- Miscellany, 1782-1931 (Box 3-4)
  Biographical papers, campaign material, elementary school notebook, college scrapbooks, memorial steamship log, and a volume of letters of speakers of the United States House of Representatives.
  Arranged alphabetically by subject.
  - Biographical material and articles about Longworth, 1925-1931, undated (Box 3)
  - Campaign material, 1918, 1928
  - Fiftieth wedding anniversary memorial of Nicholas and Susan Longworth, 1857
  - Log of the Steam Yacht C.O., St. Francis and Mississippi rivers, 1885, Oct. 10-Dec. 11 See Oversize
  - Newspaper clippings, 1924
  - Notebook, elementary school, undated
  - Printed matter, 1924-1925, (2 folders)
  - Album, letters of speakers of the United States House of Representatives, 1782-1920 See Oversize (Box 4)
  - Scrapbooks, circa 1887-1891, (2 vols.)
- Oversize, 1782-1920 (Box OV 1-OV 2)
  Memorial steamship log and volume of letters of speakers of the United States House of Representatives.
  Arranged and described according to the series, containers, and folders from which the items were removed.
  - Miscellany (Box OV 1)
    - Log of the Steam Yacht C.O., St. Francis and Mississippi rivers, 1885, Oct. 20- Dec. 11 (Container 3)
    - Album, letters of speakers of the United States House of Representatives, 1782-1920 (Container 4) (Box OV 2)